So actually when I first was invited I was trying to real - trying to think
of what kind of talk I could give, right. So I went to the website from Never Work
in Theory and I just like - I looked and I highlighted several different things,
it's like something that's real life to both questions and answers and then
a bridge between researchers and practitioners. And look at what questions could be tackled next.
So it's sort of like a focus view. So based on this I tried to create
my presentation and try to at least give you some idea what we've been working on.
So actually my - what I'm - what I'm hoping that you can take away from this
talk is just a slightly different view of maybe how you think libraries are
and maybe - maybe you already know this or maybe you don't but, yeah,
just some interesting things that we've been doing with libraries.
So actually everybody I think framework also mentioned like Chat GPT everything is coming up,
so I asked, why don't you know give the definition of libraries through Chat GPT, right?
So Chat GPT I put it in, what do we know about libraries and their dependencies?
And it came up with three important things - I think that came up, well,
it didn't cover everything. So one of the key concepts is
related to version control, security, and also package managers like npm.
So I believe if - if my assumptions are correct I'm talking to, maybe, developers,
so maybe you don't need for me to explain what a library is,
but basically what it is, like, I'll just say, fundamentally,
is like when people create projects now, they never use their - start from scratch,
they try to use an old project or existing code, so this is a kind of code reuse.
So let me take you back to the early days of code reuse.
So there's this term called NCBM - I know
you can't read all of this - but basically developers were
very wary of adopting other people's code, which is probably what they - currently the
developers would think were kind of crazy - but back in those days around 2006,
people were a bit worried. I don't trust anyone else's
code, and I feel a bit uneasy. But then here were arguments for it:
you have to trust people and their compilers, you have to trust the class libraries,
and also you need to trust the people that make good compilers.
So programmers do eventually start writing Python, Perl, PHP, they have to trust the interpreter.
So this is what led to - it's - it's all about trust, and trusting other people's code.
And this all led to like dependencies. And if you know about dependencies,
you'll know that even though you can adopt something that's very high level or very abstract,
you really don't know what's behind it - all the dependencies stuff that's down there.
So this is an interesting case and this was during my research as a postdoc - is
that if you're familiar with the npm, there was this 11 or 12 lines of code that
broke - basically broke the internet. One of the the persons - it's
called the left pad incident - they removed this small piece of trivial code and
it basically was dependent on other libraries. So based on that it also linked up with
securities, vulnerabilities, and what this term nowadays they call it software
ecosystems or package ecosystem. So this is the kind of work
that we've been looking at. So, so far in my research -
so from 2013 when I first graduated to now 2023 - 10 years - I think there's been a lot of work
that's been both from the industry and also from researchers.
So what's helped us a lot is, we've got a lot of library data sets,
for example libraries.io, Software Heritage, the GH archives,
and then there's also GH GitHub API, so you can use that to download data sets
and do empirical studies to analyze these things. From the industry point of view there was a lot
of dependency bot, which is a kind of
bot-assisted fixing your updates and recently there's this Log for
Shell vulnerability which also sparked the Alpha Omega project
that people are looking for, like, the supply chains and how these big ecosystems, like,
how can we manage these ecosystems. So based on that I'll just do two examples today
of some of the research ideas that we are doing. So the first example is how to secure
your libraries. So I'm not talking
about metal detectors in libraries. This is library ecosystem, right.
So here we tried - there was a student - so we had undergrad students,
and I'll just - I don't know if you can see my screen,
but I'll try to bring up a quick demo of this. So the student tried to create a tool
that could look at not only the dependencies that the project relies on
but actually the transitive dependencies, so dependencies that go down the chain.
And as you can see they are large - huge - we actually - this is
very hard work to get - to get - As a researcher it's very hard,
we sold it, like, as a tool, it works but to actually evaluate
how good it is, it's very hard. So we also did, like, a user study
with some developers to help us understand these vulnerabilities.
So here is part of the tool you can see that we have different
colors that show the different layers, and for example this one that's orange has,
like, the severity is very high. If you click on the link you should
be able to find out where the security fix is and what kind of vulnerabilities are there.
So what was the motivation of this tool? So I think what we wanted to do is,
we wanted to provide developers with a more, like, holistic view of the project
and see how many libraries, how much transivity, has been - has
been - has occurred within the project. So this this took us - the thing is, after this,
there's also this thing called dependabot and there's less user interface.
So our idea was to use the visualization, but as you can see it's kind of very messy,
so it's - I think there's still a lot of work that has to be done with it,
but some of the key highlights that we found is, indeed,
there is a lot of vulnerabilities that connect to each other way down the dependency tree.
So that's one of the work that we - we're looking at.
So let me go back to my slideshow again, hopefully everybody's still with me.
So as you can see this is just a snapshot of the October from last year.
So as you can see GitHub is one of the biggest sources of open source software
and also these open source software use a lot of software libraries in their projects.
So here is almost 94 million. So that's one idea.
The second one we're looking at is something called protestware.
So here this looks like a normal piece of code and there is some
vulnerability it's a CVE - some attack - and in this case it was the IP location
and the IP location is actually Russia. So this is a bit - this is not your kind
of - regular kind of vulnerability attack. So what we found was that, I don't know,
if last year there was a lot of protests where, so we're finding that there's also social
ideas coming into the code. One example on your top left side
is when one of the npm developers decided that he was going to remove his package from the ecosystem
and wanted to hold people accountable. The other one is about the Ukraine
war and they wanted to show their support. So I think - we wrote a short paper about this,
we haven't done, like, currently we're doing the full analysis on the impacts of this
but it looks like people are using - developers are using their influence to try to get their
message - political views across. So coming from open source you
can say that it's kind of weaponizing because it's a kind of discrimination
against people or groups. So this is kind of
interesting things that we're looking at. So I'm just gonna go quick because I have
probably the last minute. So what do we know about
libraries and their dependencies? I think it's all about trust and when
developers did not trust the libraries and now they're giving a lot of trust - maybe too much.
And also when we do this kind of analysis we do, I think there's need to be tools,
there's need to be visualizations and kind of feedback from developers,
what works, what doesn't work, I think that is currently
outstanding in the research field. And I think, in my experience,
there's like the gap - the gap between open source
and industry or researchers in industry in this particular research field is not that far
because I think that there's a lot of industry that use a lot of open source.
And the second point which is, to my second case study,
is that libraries are ever expanding, so now they're even dealing with social issues
and I think this is because many of the developers now they move beyond just traditional programmers
but also other other kinds of people that also program too as well.
So I want to end with, "With great power comes great responsibility."
Thank you for your attention and you can scan me or just ask me questions.
I once again thank the organizers. All right, thank you very much for that.
We do have a couple of questions that have come in.
The first one is, in your experience or from your research,
how much attention do developers actually pay to library vulnerabilities?
I get notifications from GitHub for example about needing to update packages
and I must admit I mostly delete the messages and wait until I'm doing something anyway.
So according to the data, we've done this analysis,
and actually people - the role of - the responsibility - it doesn't
really hurt you until there's a business case.
So I think that's what the current view is. However in many cases if you leave it too
late then your software can be rendered outdated, right,
so that's why we want to come up with this interesting visualizations or
some kind of motivation because I feel that the
notification is kind of - it's overused - that people also get tired of this,
so it becomes more a pain rather than something useful,
so we need something smarter and I think that's where researchers would come together to try to
answer them. Okay,
and one last quick question before we go to our next speaker.
Do you think there is a risk of open source communities fracturing along political lines?
Because of course if I create a package that doesn't work in a particular locale or doesn't
work for a particular group of people there's the risk that we're then going
to see further fissuring because of package compatibility issues?
Yeah, I think there is a lot of work ongoing now,
especially with developer diversity, and there's a lot of, like, other issues
that are coming up with software, so I think, in my opinion,
I think that it's - it's going to become a topic where people have to be more, like,
when you develop code now, you have to be more aware - maybe
awareness of what it could affect and how much responsibility you have to exert,
right, so I don't know if I answered your question
but there was, like, I think there's a lot of work that still needs to be done in this area.